Alfred D. Crimi Papers
Alfred D. Crimi Papers
1912-1935.
Crimi, Alfred D., 1900-1994.
1.5 linear ft.
Papers of the Italian-American painter, muralist.
Correspondence, blueprints, finanacial and legal papers, photographs, slides, and writings, including the manuscript for Crimi's autobiography, and other material by and about him.
148916
Biographical History
Alfred D. Crimi was born in eastern Sicily on Dec. 1, 1900. He came to the United States in 1910 and was naturalized in 1924. He attended public school in East Harlem's Little Italy.
He was a student at the National Academy of Design from 1916-1924 and attended the Beaux Arts Institute from 1920-1921. In 1929, he returned to Europe to study fresco painting in Italy.
He has found most of his success in the field of mural work, winning numerous national contests for painting in public and semi-public buildings. Notably, he was hired by the Works Progress Administration (WPA) for the Harlem Hospitals murals project. He also worked for the Public Works of Art project in Key West, Florida.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alfred D Crimi Papers is divided into four series. The first series is Correspondence, which is further divided into incoming and outgoing correspondence. The incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically and by sender subject, and covers the years from 1935 to 1948; outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically, covering the same period. The second series is the Subject File, which is arranged alphabetically by subject. This series contains blueprints, legal material, finances, notes, press releases, and reports. The Manuscripts series contains articles written by others. The last series, Published Materials, contains articles about Crimi and others, articles about ethics, legal processes, illustrations, and newspaper clippings.
The April 1982 Addenda to the collection contains one series, which includes correspondence, published materials, and other miscellaneous items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Art -- Painters; Crimi, Alfred D., 1900-1994.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Church decoration and ornament -- United States.; Italian American painters.; Italian Americans.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- United States -- 20th century.; Articles.; Autobiographies (literary works); Awards.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Exhibition catalogs.; Lectures.; Photographs.; Reviews (documents); Slides (photographs); Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. Crimi, 1964-1987.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Outgoing, 1937-1940; 1946,; 1948; 6 folders
  - Of others
    - National Society of Mural Painters, 1937-1938; 1940-1941 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Background material (Box 1)
  - Blueprints of Rugers Church (Box 1)
  - Contract, Crimi & Rugers Presbyterian Church (Box 1)
  - Crimi versus Rugers Church (Box 1)
  - Expenses incurred by artist, Rugers Church (Box 1)
  - Notes (Box 1)
  - Press releases (Box 1)
  - Rugers Presbyterian Church, Insurance papers (Box 1)
  - Reports and data of Society of Mural Painters (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - By others (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Articles about Crimi (Box 1)
  - Articles by Crimi (Box 1)
  - Articles about others (Box 1)
  - Illustrations (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous articles, concerning ethics (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous articles, concerning Crimi's case (Box 1)
  - News letters- Society of Mural Painters (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
- 1982 additions
  - Adult Education Courses in Art, City College of New York (Box 1)
  - Allied Artists of America (Box 1)
  - Art critics, newspaper clippings to art publishers (Box 1)
  - American Artist Magazine (Box 1)
  - Artists Fellowship (Box 1)
  - Allentown Art Museum (Box 1)
  - American Watercolor Society (Box 1)
  - Audubon Artists - Alfred D. Crimi's Presidency, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Awards - Scholastic & Professional (Box 1)
  - Board of Education - City of New York - License # 415192 - & Health Certificate (Box 1)
  - Bookbinder - The School District of Philadelphia, on Lecture (Box 1)
  - Butler Institute of Fine Arts (Box 1)
  - Clippings, reviews (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Art Classic on the Plaza 1956 to 1975, West Orange, New Jersey (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970 to 1979 (Box 1)
  - Exhibitions & galleries (Box 1)
  - Federation of Modern Painters & Sculptors (Box 1)
  - Rev. Thomas Diehl - Personal correspondence (Box 1)
  - Fellow artists & friends (Box 1)
  - Fellow artists & friends exhibition catalogues (Box 1)
  - Fellow artists & friends (Box 1)
  - Friends & fan letters (Box 1)
  - Fordham University (Box 1)
  - Gallery Association of N.Y.S. (Box 1)
  - Harlem Hospital Mural (Box 1)
  - Holyoke Museum - One-man exhibition (Box 1)
  - Janoff & Kravitz - Attorneys, Water damage case (Box 1)
  - Japanese & American Art exchange Record (Nipon Museum) (Box 1)
  - Kearney, Leo R. - on the Caracci Painting (Box 1)
  - Lectures & Tours - The Association of American Colleges (Box 1)
  - Lecture Tours - Association of American Colleges, correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1949-61; Liturgical Arts (Box 1)
  - Liturgical - All inclusive, personal correspondence (Box 1)
  - Marietta College - Mainstreams Internationals (Box 1)
  - Magazine articles - catalogs & circulars (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea - correspondence, from 1936 to 1966 (Box 1)
  - Board of Education - P.S.# 5 Mosaic Murals (Box 1)
  - Board of Education - P.S.# 110 Mosaic Murals (Box 1)
  - Board of Education - Southeast Bronx High School N.Y.C.- Mural (Box 1)
  - Board of Education Contract for Mosaic - P.S.#377- Brooklyn - Mosaic Mural (Box 1)
  - Mural Board of Education - High Schools 131 & Mosaic Mural (Box 1)
  - National Council of Jewish Women (Box 1)
  - New York Botanical Garden, Bronx (Box 1)
  - The New York Botanical Garden Record Gift of Drawings (Box 1)
  - Personal circulars and News Bulletin of the National Society of Mural Painters (Box 1)
  - New York Times, Letters to Hilton Kramer and New York Times (Box 1)
  - Northhampton, Mass, - Proclamation & District Service Certificate "Save the Mural Week" (Box 1)
  - Osservatorio Romano (Bruzichelli International Liturgical Arts Exhibition) (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania State University (Box 1)
  - Portland Art Museum - Oregon (Box 1)
  - Letters on Ringwood Mannor West Gallery - New Jersey (Box 1)
  - Additional data to Rutgers Presbyterian Church Mural Demise (Box 1)
  - Talks & lectures (Box 1)
  - Universities, miscellanea & colleges (Box 1)
  - Who's Who (Box 1)
  - Magazines (Box 1)